# Samuel Chagas de Assis

#### BIOTECHNOLOGIST - COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGIST

Campinas, São Paulo - Brazil

☑samuel.achagas98@gmail.com | ☆chagas98.github.io | ☑chagas98 | 圖samuelchagass

## About me\_

I'm a computational biologist fascinated by understanding the molecular biodiversity and mechanisms. I have experience with workflow development in Python and R, molecular dynamics simulations data analysis, and immunogenetics. Currently, my work focuses on workflow development through documentation, automation, and reproducibility. I'm an intern researcher at the Computational Biocatalysis Group at LNBR/CNPEM in Brazil, where I work with specific Carbohydrate-Active Enzymes for microbiome and structural biology research projects using biomolecular modeling data and biochemical interpretation. When I have some time, I enjoy to draw molecular scientific illustrations and cooking plant-based recipes.

# **Education**

## Federal University of Latin-American Integration (UNILA)

Liberato Salzano Vieira da Cunha Foudation

Foz do Iguaçu, Brazil

2018-2024

BACHELOR IN BIOTECHNOLOGY

Novo Hamburgo, Brazil

ELECTRICAL TECHNICIAN

2013-2017

# **Experience**

### **Brazilian Center for Research in Energy and Materials (CNPEM)**

Campinas, São Paulo

COMPUTATIONAL BIOCATALYSIS INTERN

Feb 2023 - Present

- I have performed data analysis of several molecular dynamics simulations, primarily using Python and Shell scripting compatible with SLURM HPC environment. The main goal are new insights about molecular mechanisms from new Carbohydrate-Active enzyme families.
- | Gromacs | SLURM/HPC | Python/MDAnalysis | Python/Autodock Vina | Conda/Bioconda | Pymol/VMD |

SporeData Inc. Remote

FREELANCER - JR DATA ANALYST

Oct 2022 - Feb 2023

- Worked as a freelancer on healthcare data projects, performing ETL, cohort generation, data visualization, clinical study reports, and statistical
  analyses.
- | R/Tidyverse | RStats | RMarkdown | Cloud/N3C |

#### **Medical Genetics Lab - UNILA**

Foz do Iguaçu, Paraná

Undergraduate Researcher

Aug 2020 - Mar 2023

- I have performed DNA sequencing and HLA-B analysis of COVID-19 patients, gathering clinical and genomic data, along with HLA-epitopes binding affinities from computational predictions, to study the mutational landscape of SARS-CoV-2 variants in Foz do Iguaçu. I worked in a Nextflow pipeline to collect, transform and visualize missense mutations affecting HLA-apitopes.
- | Missense mutation analyses | GISAID | Nextflow | Bash | Python | R | Sanger Sequencing/Wet Lab | netMHCpan4.1 |

# **International Genetically Engineered Machine Competition (iGEM)**

Foz do Iguaçu, Paraná

DRYLAB COORDINATOR

Jan 2020 - Dez 2021

• | system biology modeling | Python/Scipy | Python/NUPACK | R/ggplot2 | ODEs/Modeling |

# Microbiology and Biochemical Lab - UNILA

Foz do Iguaçu, Paraná

Undergraduate Researcher

Jun 2018 - Dez 2019

. ||

# Habilidades e Qualificações\_

- Linguagens de Programação: R, Python e Bash
- Markup: RMarkdown e HTML

- Gerenciamento: Git/GitHub, GitHub Actions, Slurm
- Sistemas UNIX/Linux

## Microbiology and Biochemical Lab - UNILA

Undergraduate Researcher

Foz do Iguaçu, Paraná Jun 2018 - Dez 2019

# Prêmios\_\_\_\_\_

2022	Primeiro Lugar. Menção Honrosa na área de Ciências da Saúde no XI EICTI - UNILA
2021	Medalha de Ouro e Nomeação de Melhor Projeto de Nova Aplicação e Práticas Humanas na <i>International</i>
	Genetically Engineering Machine Competition (iGEM)
2020	Melhor Projeto de Escolha do Público no V Curso de Verão de Engenharia de Máquinas Biológicas - UFMG
2020	Melhor Apresentação no V Curso de Verão de Engenharia de Máquinas Biológicas - UFMG
2019	Primeiro Lugar. Menção Honrosa na área de Tecnologia e Produção no VII SEUNI - UNILA
2016	Menção Honrosa UNESCO pelo Projeto de Relevância Social na Conferência Internacional de Ciência e
	Tecnologia de Nível Médio - MOSTRATEC/UNESCO

# **Publicações**

• **De Assis**, S.C., Morgado, D.L., Scheidt, D.T., De Souza, S.S., Cavallari, M.R., Ando, O.H.J., Carrilho, E. (2023). Review of Bacterial Nanocellulose-Based Electrochemical Biosensors: Functionalization, Challenges, and Future Perspectives. *MDPl Biosensors*, 13. https://doi.org/10.3390/bios13010142